Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 6 -- Letters to Franklin 1781-1782 Mss.B.F85inventory06
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 January 26; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Sr
    Announcing his safe arrival after a passage of twenty days. Congratulating him on the good news of peace.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 January 27; L. S. 1p.; Grand, Ferdinand
    Introducing M. Dubois, who has something of interest to communicate to Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 January 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Durieux de Beaurepaire,----
    Before accepting certain orders from a Philadelphia firm established at l'Orient, desires to know their reputation and standing.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 January 27; A.L.S. 4p.; Lorinet, Bernard-Nicolas
    Concerning his work in medicine.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 January 28; L. 2p.; Grand, Ferdinand
    Statement of accounts.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 January 28; A.L.S. 2p.; Sarsfield, Guy-Claude, comte de
    Recommending for a position in the American army, an officer who quitted the service of the Margrave d'Anspach when that Prince supplied England with troops.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 January 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Lorinet, Bernard-Nicolas
    Wishes to become a citizen of America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 January 30; A.L.S. 2p.; Sarsfield, Guy-Claude, comte de
    His letter of the 28th inst.; aware of Franklin's attitude towards such requests; hoped this particular case might be treated as an exception; desires an answer that he may show to his friend.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 January 31; L.S. 1p.; Barry, John. L'Orient
    Difficulty experienced in procuring his full complement of sailors. Expressing his willingness to take over certain public goods.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 January 31; A.L.S. 1p.; Dumouchel, ------. Paris
    Concerning a bill of exchange.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 January; A.L.S. 1p.; Montgolfier, Maurice-Augustin
    Directed a friend at Lyons to send him certain samples of paper. Desires the enclosed letter forwarded to his uncle, head of the Monastery of St. Sulpice at Montreal.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 1; A.L.S. 1p.; O'Gorman, Thomas, chevalier
    Acknowledging his note; communicated it to the merchants of Nantes who will wait on Franklin shortly.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 1; A.L.S. 3p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    Detailed explanation of the use of passports or registers; Franklin mistaken in supposing such applications are made to cover irregular or illicit commerce; encloses copies [2 p.] of the permission granted by the Ministry, according to the forms established in such cases.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1782.] February 1; A.L. 3p.; Brillon, Mme
    Has given a note of introduction to a Mr. Delon who came to Nice with Lord Cholmondeley as his companion or preceptor. Probably desires to bring about a meeting between Lord Cholmondeley and Franklin. Particulars about the young Lord and his Mentor. Surmises as to their real object in wishing to meet Franklin. Her health continues to improve. Her Husband being no longer under the evil influence of a certain person shows her every kindness and attention.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Birckel, -------. Strasbourg
    Remarks about the soul.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 2; L.S. 1p.; Conti, Louis-François-Joseph de Bourbon, comte de la Marche and prince de. Paris
    Desiring a passport for his grooms who go to England to purchase dogs.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 2; L.S. 1p.; Watson and Cossoul. Nantes
    Requesting a passport for the brig "Ernelia" at Morlaix, commanded by John H. Richard and bound for America; desiring also a permit to ship American sailors wherever found; some sailors taken from them by a Lieut. Gill of the "Alliance"; protests vehemently against such conduct.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 2; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Concerning the acceptance of certain bills in which both he and Mr. Bache are concerned.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 2; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Enclosing a letter from Capt. John Foster Williams, lately arrived from prison; hopes in consequence of his letter, fifty-three of their poor countrymen may be liberated.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 3; A.L.S. 1p.; Corny, Dominique-Louis Ethis de
    Franklin's promise to return him his bill of exchange.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 3; A.L.S. 4p.; Barclay, Thomas. Amsterdam
    Concerning the Continental goods left by Mr. Gillon at Amsterdam; contention between Messrs. de Neufville and Van Arp as to the possession of a part of these goods; money needed to send them to America; desires to have a particular sum passed to his account.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 4; A.L.S. 2p.; Nesbitt, Jonathan, & Co.
    Thanking him for procuring the exchange of Capt. [Thomas] Bell for Capt. [John] Kinnier. Desires information about certain bills drawn by Mr. W[illia]m Trent of Philadelphia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 4; L.S. 3p.; Adams, John. Amsterdam
    Bills drawn on Mr. [Henry] Laurens, which, if Franklin cannot meet, must protested. His reasons for thinking there will be neither peace nor mediation; probability of the States making a treaty with France and America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 4; A.L.S. 1p.; Andrews, Samuel. Paris
    Will wait upon Franklin that afternoon, respecting the letter he spoke of.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 4; A.L.S. 1p.; Saint-Auban, Jacques-Antoine Baratier, marquis de
    Desiring him to dine with them. Sends a memoir (64a, see infra) which he could not well refuse to present to Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1782 February 4]; Mem. 4p.; La Plaigne, Emmanuel-Pierre de
    Account of his services to the United States from 1775-1778, when he was captured by the English; his arrival in France; destitute of everything; desires to obtain the salary due him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 4; A.L.S. 4p.; Laussat, -----. Lagor, near Orthez
    Writes for news of his nephew, who went to Philadelphia at the commencement of the war and entered business with a commercial house there; rumor of his having been assassinated; begs Franklin to ascertain the truth of these reports, and if the young man is dead, to get some friend to look after his effects.
    A. E. by Dr. Franklin. Will write to America and make the inquiries.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 4; A.L.S. 3p.; O'Gorman, Thomas, chevalier
    The merchants of Nantes will wait on Franklin on Thursday. Efforts made by his protectors at Court to obtain for him the position of Consul at Charlestown; begs Franklin, when he goes to Court, to use his influence on his behalf.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 5; A.L.S. 2p.; Young, Moses
    Account of the sum due him by Congress for his services as Secretary to Mr. Henry Laurens; acknowledgment of a part payment by Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 5; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Unable to meet the expenses of a town-house; his wife and daughter have gone to the country while he has taken rooms in town; any omissions in his correspondence due to worry over this enforced separation from his family. Affairs in Holland; resolution taken by the town of Dort relative to a mediation.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 6; L.S. 3p.; Torris, John. Dunkirk
    Sending a circular (1 p.) of his new business connections. Account of the service rendered the United States by the brave Capt. Macatter, who commanded the "Black Princess"; his capture by the English; all efforts to obtain his release have proved useless; the English insist in regarding him as a traitor; begs Franklin's assistance in obtaining his freedom.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Barber, David F. Ostend
    Taken prisoner six months before, but made his escape; possessed a few American bills which he forwarded to Franklin for acceptance; Franklin's refusal to decide the matter for twelve days has put him to great inconvenience.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Defay, Mlle ----. Paris
    Will wait on Franklin in a fortnight with the samples of paper. Sent him yesterday two works by a physician [Gastellier] of Gâtinais, as a slight mark of his respect and veneration; his wish to become a member of the Scientific Society of Philadelphia [American Philosophical Society].
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 8; A.L.S. 2p.; Sargent, Rosamond. Halsted Place, Eng
    Entreats his kindness on behalf of three English officers, taken prisoner with Lord Cornwallis; their names are Messrs. Harry Calvert, George and Thomas Scott; if wounded or sick, begs to be allowed to assist and help them.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Introducing Mr. Grubb, who intends to settle in France and go into business with Mr. Hazlehurst.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 9; L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Information concerning the shipping of certain goods from Brest.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 11; A.L.S. 1p.; Rucker, John. L'Orient
    No American vessels at l'Orient and none immediately expected; the "Alliance" sailed on Saturday in company with Capt. Angus.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 12; A.L.S. 7p.; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves, marquis de, 1757-1834
    Question of transporting the stores to America. In favor of the "Alliance" being allowed the indulgence of a cruise; promise from the Marquis de Castries to let Barry have all the American sailors he can get in any French ports.
    Printed in Hale's Franklin in France, II, 15.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 12; A.L.S. 2p.; Wyld, Henry
    The company duly appreciative of Franklin's kindness; their determination is firm to emigrate directly; certain privileges which they desire from Congress; wish to know of some trustworthy Captain. Asking if engines used in cutting small screws have been introduced into America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 13; A.L.S. 2p.; Von Steuben, I.M. Bärwalde. Pomerania
    Has written to his brother, General von Steuben, twice, but received no answer. Requests Franklin to forward enclosed letter. His first letter, dated Dec. 19th, 1780, was in care of Major von Glöden. His second letter was dated Aug. 15th, 1781, in care of Dr. Franklin. Is worried, because he has heard neither from his brother nor from Dr. Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Barber, David F. Ostend
    Again requesting that his bills of exchange may either be accepted or protested and returned to him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Poissonnier, Pierre
    Desiring Franklin's presence at the "Collège Royal" where he expects to lecture.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 14; A.L.S. 3p.; Barclay, Thomas. Amsterdam
    Has not been able to procure proper conveyances for the Continental supplies; every part of the business has been involved in difficulty, vexation and expense; will come to Paris, if Franklin deems a consultation necessary.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 14; A.L.S. 1p.; Beraud de Ciccati, Lt Col ----
    Encloses letter for his son in the American service.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 14; A.L.S. 1p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Resolution in favor of mediation passed in the States-General.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 14; A.L.S. 2p.; Larwood and Van Hassett and Van Suchtelen. Amsterdam
    Certain bills of exchange drawn on Mr. [Henry] Laurens, but through his unfortunate detention in England, not accepted; begs Franklin's influence for their acceptance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 14; A.L.S. 1p.; Watson and Cossoul. Nantes
    Again requesting a passport for their brig at Morlaix.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 15; L.S. 1p.; Desegray and Company
    Have drawn on Franklin for the sum due them for disbursements to twenty-six American seamen.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 15; A.L.S. 2p.; Du Ponceau, Louise-Geneviève
    Her unprotected state without father or mother; both her brothers absent; begs Franklin to forward her letters to her brother in Philadelphia and to send any answers to her.
    A. E. by Dr. Franklin. Promising to do what she asks.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 16; A.L.S. 1p.; Kéralio, Agathon Guynement, chevalier de
    Their good friend [the Dowager Duchess of Deux-Ponts] desires Franklin and his grandson to dine with her any day the following week. News received from Cadiz of a victory won by Gen. [Nathanael] Greene over the English at sixty miles from Charleston. The fleet has set sail from Brest.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 16; A.L.S. 3p.; Rousseaux, Jean
    Begging for the wages and prize-money due him during his service on board the "Lexington"; his subsequent sufferings in prison; his destitute condition.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 18; A.L.S. 1p.; Grand de La Chaise, Daniel
    Sends Franklin the three periodicals he desired.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 18; A.L.S. 2p.; Rougemont, -----. Paris
    Account of a large collection of uniforms, etc., intended for the American army, captured on board a French vessel, and now in London; offers to sell them to Franklin for the United States.
    A.E. by Dr. Franklin. His orders completed; cannot at present treat for the clothes; believes if the owners would send them to America, they might sell them to advantage.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Kéralio, Agathon Guynement, chevalier de
    Their good friend [la Douairière. Duchesse de Deux-Ponts] will be delighted to see Franklin on the 23d.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Andrews, Samuel. Paris
    Sends two of his "résumé mémoirs"; expects his business to come before Council and be judged to his satisfaction on Monday.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Martin, C Barthélemy, fils aîné
    Desires the position of Consul at the above port.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 21; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Cheylus, ---- marquis de
    Is desirous of waiting upon Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 21; A.L.S. 2p.; Le Rouge, -----. Paris
    Asking the name of some work, which treats of the war in America, for Comte de Ségur; begs Franklin to procure him certain maps from London.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 21; A.L.S. 2p.; Garnier, -----. Paris
    Inviting him to subscribe to "Spectacle de la Galerie de Dusseldorf."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 22; A.L.S. 2p.; Hodgson, William. London
    Account of money due for his expenditures on behalf of prisoners.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 22; A.L.S. 3p.; Carmichael, William. Madrid
    Disgrace to the National credit from the non-payment of the bills; hopes France will once more step to their relief. Question of his own salary. The conquest of Minorca and the intended siege of Gibraltar much discussed at present; the Spaniards reproach the French troops with indifference and cowardice; a different opinion of French gallantry in America; his admiration and love for la Fayette; only exceeded by his feeling for Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 23; A.L.S. 2p.; Hare, Richard, Jr
    Writes on behalf of nearly two hundred prisoners in wretched confinement; many would have perished during the winter but for a small subscription raised by a few individuals; begs Franklin to use his influence to have an exchange effected.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 24; L.S. 2p.; Bright, Michael, Champion Wood, Levy Yonger and Bartholemus Cashman. Havre-de-Grace
    Account of their escape from Forton Prison, and their arrival in France, only to be placed under arrest; desire their liberty and enough money to take them to l'Orient; complain bitterly of such unjust treatment.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 24; A.L.S. 2p.; Maugonne, ---- chevalier de
    Sending a prospectus for a Military Academy which he is starting.
    A.E. by Franklin. Will be glad to see him when he calls.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 24; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Returning Captain Folger's bond and oath.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 24; A.L.S. 2p.; Le Paon, ------
    Offers his services to Congress to paint a series of pictures, celebrating the American feats of arms; his portrait of Washington; some of his work at the Palais Bourbon and L'école Royale.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 25; A.L. in 3d P. 2p.; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves, marquis de, 1757-1834
    In compliance with Franklin's directions, had an interview with the Comte de Vergennes; the sum will be immediately communicated to Franklin; wishes its augmentation could be obtained; the petition to the Marquis de Castries will be presented at once and the answer sent to Passy as soon as possible; this peculiar situation calls him to Versailles two or three times a week.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 25; A.L.S. 3p.; Barclay, Thomas. Amsterdam
    Account of the vessel purchased by him to convey the goods to America; bills drawn on Franklin; amount owing him by Congress. Letter received from Mr. Moylan with an account of disbursements for the "Alliance."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 25; A.L.S. 1p.; Boy, Pierre-François de
    Writes on behalf of M. de Montigny, wounded on board the American frigate "South Carolina"; his destitution; desires the pay due him as well as his share of the prize-money; encloses certificate (1 p.) to prove his claim.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 26; L.S. 2p.; Michael Bright, and others. Honfleur
    Protest against their treatment (see XXIV, 97); their earnest wish to get home as soon as possible.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 26; A.L.S. 1p.; Bright, Michael. Honfleur
    Protesting against being sent on board a man-of-war; desires Franklin to let his parents and his brother William know that he is well, and that Champion Wood made his escape with him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 26; A.L.S. 1p.; Vaudoré, ---- chevalier de
    Has received no answer to the memoir he addressed to Franklin; hopes he will accede to his request and desires his certificate returned.
    A.E. by Dr. Franklin. "Not being able to do anything in such affairs I return his certificate."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Grand, Henry. Paris
    Sending him the required instructions (2 p. in French) in order to reimburse Mr. [John] Adams for the sum lent Mr. [Francis M.] Dana.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 27; L.S. 2p.; Barry, John. L'Orient
    His safe arrival with the frigate "Alliance"; can only wait the return of the post for Franklin's despatches. Very poor success on his last cruise.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Holker, Jean. Rouen
    Franklin's letters handed him by Messrs. Hazlehurst and Grubb, to whom he has rendered every little service in his power; various manufactories they have visited. Messages from his wife and Mr. Ridley. The date of Marquis de la Fayette's return.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Maillebois, comte de
    Sends him papers relating to considerable affairs in America in which his friend, la Marquise de Cassiny is interested; desires their return at his earliest convenience so that he may carry them to the Marquis de la Fayette. Has been confined to his house for five weeks with the gout.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Cottin fils and Jauge
    Hears that Franklin is considering the purchase of a vessel; describes one which he thinks will suit him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 28; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves, marquis de, 1757-1834
    Inquires if Mr. Franklin will be in; wishes to see him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 28; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Brewse, Mrs and Miss
    Begging him to forward a letter to Lieut.-Col. Brewse.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 28; A.L.S. 3p.; Barclay, Thomas. Amsterdam
    Situation of the goods sold by Mr. Gillon; conditions upon which he will be able to procure them and forward them to America. Expects the "General Sullivan" in ten days.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 28; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Puységur, Messrs de
    Announcing the death of their father.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 29; L.S. 3p.; Barry, John. L'Orient
    Account of his dispute with the French sailors who came with the "Alliance" from Boston; difficulty of procuring American sailors; habit of the French to trump up an account against any American who is desired to go on board; given an instance of this nefarious practice; out of his power to go to Brest; if the goods were at L'Orient, might take a certain number. Advises against sending any more powder and arms to the Eastern provinces; his reasons. Is stretching his orders further than he likes in order to wait for Franklin's despatches.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Strange, Robert. London
    Transmitting a copy of Cicero's Cato; Mr. Strahan afraid it is not the desired edition; Mr. S[trahan] would have written, but he has not yet recovered from his defeat that morning in the House of Commons; thinks the proceedings open a prospect of peace. His intention of coming to Paris.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February; A.L.S. 1p.; Vicq d' Azyr, Félix
    Sending him tickets for a meeting of the Royal Society of Medicine and begging the honor of his presence on that occasion.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February; A.L. in 3d P. 2p.; Grand, Ferdinand
    Informing him that the Spaniards are in possession of Fort St. Philippe [Port Mahon, Minorca].
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 March 1; L.S. 1p.; Parke, Matthew. L'Orient
    Thanking him for his kind advice and offers of service; has written the Minister to request that their part of the prize-money may be paid to their attorney.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 March 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Hodgson, William. London
    His funds more than exhausted; Mr. [Edmund] Burke's intention of bringing in a bill for a general exchange of prisoners; some hope of success after what passed the night before. Mr. [Henry] L[aurens] considers himself restricted from writing to persons abroad, but will do all the good in his power.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 March 2; A.L.S. 1p.; Olivar, D
    Asking for a letter of recommendation to the Comte d'Aranda, whose protection he desires in order to join "la Pobordia" on the island of Minorca.
    (In Spanish.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 March 3; L.S. 2p.; Alexander, William. Ostend
    Left London the day before; the King's-answer to the various addresses; has letters for Franklin which will disclose the sentiments of parties in England. Had the good fortune to procure the liberty of Gouverneur and Carson after Mr. Hodgson had tried in vain. Expects to be at St. Germain by Wednesday.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 March 3; A.L.S. 3p.; Carmichael, William. Madrid
    Announcing Mr. Guichen's arrival at Cadiz with the fleet. Necessity of the French Court advancing a sufficient sum of money to enable Mr. Jay to discharge the bills already accepted; has been haunted by this business for weeks past. Account of their negotiations; the instructions of M. Del Campo not yet ready. Coldness towards him of the Marquis d'Aranda; reasons for this change of manner. Elation in Spain caused by the taking of Fort St. Philippe; the siege of Gibraltar determined upon. General esteem acquired by Mr. Page, a young American volunteer who acted as the Duc de Brillon's Aide-de-camp at Minorca.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 March 4; L.S. 2p.; Barry, John. L'Orient